Guide to the Rick Reese Collection 1981-2013
Montana State University-Bozeman Library
Rick Reese Collection
1981-2013
Montana State University-Bozeman Library, Merrill G Burlingame Special Collections P.O. Box 173320 Bozeman, MT 59717-3320 United States Phone (406) 994-4242 Fax (406) 994-2851 http://www.lib.montana.edu/archives/ University Archivist spcoll@www.lib.montana.edu
Collection 2635, MtBC, us
Reese, Rick
1.8 linear feet
The Rick Reese Colletion consists of documents, clippings, media, and transparencies were created or collected by Reese from 1981-2013. Items found within this collection relate to foundational materials of the Greater Yellowstone Coalition, reports, correspondence, project information, and an outreach slideshow on the Greater Yellowstone area.
Biographical Note
The Greater Yellowstone Coalition (GYC) was founded in 1983 with a mission to protect the Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem for current and future generations. The group’s vision is a healthy and intact Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem where critical lands and waters are adequately protected; wildlife is managed in a thoughtful, sustainable manner; and a strong, diverse base of support is working to conserve this special place as part of a larger, connected Northern Rocky Mountain Region. The group supports policies which will protect the environmental integrity of Yellowstone National Park and maintain to the highest possible extent the natural condition of the lands surrounding Yellowstone which together with the park comprise the Great Yellowstone Ecosystem. They are a nationally known advocate for the idea that ecosystem level sustainability and science should guide the management of the region’s public and private lands. States that are a part of this coalition include Montana, Wyoming, and Idaho. Issues that the GYC takes on include environmental impacts, as well as conservations battles to preserve the Yellowstone National Park ecosystem and the areas that surround it. The GYC covers more than 20 million acres, three states, and Yellowstone National Park.
Rick Reese became involved in Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem issues circa 1980. In 1983, he became the founding president of the GYC. Reese grew up in Salt Lake City, Utah before moving to Montana with his family. After moving to Helena in 1970, Reese started a job as an assistant professor of political science at Carroll College. As a founding member and president of GYC, Reese assisted in creating and building a solid foundation for the coalition. His work and contributions with the GYC lasted beyond his three years as president. In subsequent years he served as Deputy Director of the State Commission on Local Government, Executive Secretary to the Montana Board of Public Education, and was director of the Yellowstone Institute. Reese is also a noted alpinist and known for his part in a 1967 rescue effort in the Grand Teton which was highlighted in documentary “The Grand Rescue”.
The Rick Reese Collection consists of documents, media, and transparencies were created or collected by Reese from 1981-2013. The materials in this collection have been organized into four series according to content and year. Within the series are foundational materials of the GYC, reports, correspondence, project information, and an outreach slideshow on the Greater Yellowstone area.
Series 1 Early Years GYC, 1981-1984
Series 2 Reports and Printed Material, 1985-2013
Series 3 Media, 1982-2012
Series 4 35mm Transparencies
Folders 8-11 in Box 3 are restricted due to privacy concerns. Files will be restricted until 2098.
Articles, documents, clippings, media, and transparencies created or collected by Rick Reese were donated to Montana State University June 28, 2018.
Environmental Activism; Environmental Conditions; Fisheries and Wildlife; Montana; Moving Imges; Sound Recordings
- Early Years GYC, 1981-1984; Series 1
  The contents of this series explain concept of the Great Yellowstone Ecosystem as well as the goals and purpose of the GYC via Reese’s interest and involvement in the organization. Documents include foundational materials, annual convention information, minutes, newspaper articles, and correspondence. Topics include the future of grizzly bears; possible fishing bridge closing and relocation; threats to the Park’s natural integrity through the impact of oil and gas exploration, logging, and mining. Of interest is in box 1, folder 13 correspondence with Montana Governor Ted Schwinden discussing grizzly bears and their future.
  - Beginning of GYC, 1981 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Opening Pages of GYC book by Rick Reese, 1981 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Creation Documents Behind the GYC, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - High Country News Special Issue on the Identity of the Rocky Mountains, 1982 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Founding Convention, 1983 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1983; 1984 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - GYC Newspaper Articles, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Grizzly Bear Recovery Notes, 1983; 1984 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Looking back on early history of GYC (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Opening Pages GY Book by Rick Reese, 1984 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - GYC, 1984 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1984 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Bear Documents, 1984 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Bear Newspapers, 1984 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Cody, Woming Fishing Bridge, 1984 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Board of Directors Documents and Minutes, 1984 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Founding Convention, 1984 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - GYC Reports, 1984 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - GYC Books Cited, 1984 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box-folder 1/20)
- Reports and Printed Material, 1985-2013; Series 2
  The content of this series represents functions of the GYC that Reese was included in or found important to the concept of the organization. Documents include reports, correspondence, items pertaining to the Board of Directors, Reese’s personal notes, and GYC project papers. Items of interest include Thomas McNamee’s writing about grizzly bears in box 3 as well as the addresses of Archie Carr and Ed Lewis to the coalition in box 4. Separation notices are marked with an asterisk (*). The items in this series that are restricted due to privacy concerns have been noted with a bold bracketed “R” ([R]) next to the folder’s title.
  - Newspaper Articles, 1985 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Reports, 1985 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Remarks/Addresses, 1985 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Bears, 1985 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1985 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Convention at the Lake, June 1985 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Board Meeting, November 1985 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - GYC Correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Memos, 1985 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - GYC Annual Meeting Final Report, 1985 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Summary of Revenue, 1985 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - GYC Comments on National Forests Plans (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Remarks by William Penn Mott (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Discussion Notes with Maryanne Mott (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1985 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - GYC Geothermal Policy and Yellowstone Grizzly Policy (Box-folder 2/16)
  - GYC Program Plan, 1985 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - GYC Membership, 1985 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - GYC Board of Directors, 1985 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - GYC Reports, 1985 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Thanks from Mott, Brian, Kiesling, and Martha, 1986 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Alston Chase – Playing God in Yellowstone (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Thomas McNamee, 1986 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Bob Anderson Hiring [R] (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Bob Anderson Evaluations [R], 1984; 1985; 1986 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Bob Anderson Firing [R], May 1986 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Bob Anderson After Firing [R], 1986 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - GYC Committee Minutes, 1986 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Finances, 1986 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1986 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Archie Car III Address to GYC (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Membership, 1986 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Personal Notes, 1986 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Long Range Planning, 1986 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - GYC Board of Directors (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Articles and Newspapers, 1987 (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Annual Meeting Agenda, 1987 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Wilderness Magazine, 1987 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - GYC, 1988 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Yellowstone Fires, 1988 (Box-folder 4/13)
  - The New York Times Magazine “Our National Parks: The Case for Burning” *, 1988 (Box-folder 4/14)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1989 (Box-folder 4/15)
  - Introducing Ed Lewis (Box-folder 4/16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1990 (Box-folder 4/17)
  - Harvard Lecture, October 29, 1991 (Box-folder 4/18)
  - GYC Articles, 1991 (Box-folder 4/19)
  - Preface to Third Edition, 1991 (Box-folder 4/20)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - GYC Annual Convention, 1993 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Correspondence, 1994 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Correspondence, 1995 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Rick Reese Slideshow (Box-folder 5/6)
  - GYC 20th Anniversary Reunion, 2003 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1993 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Yellowstone Newspaper Articles, 1983; 1984; 1985 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - GYC Collection Items, 1981; 1982; 1984; 1986; 1987; 1988; 1989; 1990; 1991; 1992; 1993; 1996; 2002; 2003; 2008; 2013 (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Appreciation to Rick Reese (Box-folder 5/11)
- Media, 1982-2012; Series 3
  This series includes audio-cassettes, videocassette, CD, and reel-to-reel audio tape.
  - Cassettes (Box 5)
    - First Version, Narrated by Rick Reese
    - Greater Yellowstone, Early Version with Rick narration, November 22, 1982
      Volume 1, copy 2
    - Greater Yellowstone, with Narrator
      Final Version
    - Greater Yellowstone, Reese, April 6, 1984
      Rev. 3
  - CDs (Box 5)
    - Greater Yellowstone Slide Show, Rick Reese Audio, 1982
    - Greater Yellowstone
    - GYC Slide Show, 1982
    - GYC Slide Show, 1982
      Final Images of DVD Version of 1982
    - Greater Yellowstone, Rick Reese, 1982-2012
    - GYC Slide Show 2012/1982, with Intro Rick Reese, January 24, 2012
      Volume 2
  - Videocassette (Box 5)
    - Grizzly: The Shining Mountains
  - Film Roll Tape (Box 5)
    - Greater Yellowstone, 1982
      Volume 3 Original Tape
- 35mm Transparencies, Series 4
  The content in this series includes 35 mm transparency slides that correspond with the Great Yellowstone slideshow.
  - Greater Yellowstone Slideshow #1-80 (Box 5/12)
    - #1-20
    - #21-40
    - #41-60
    - #61-80
  - Greater Yellowstone Slideshow #81-137 (Box 5/13)
    - #81-100
    - #101-120
    - #121-137